

 Sharman Networks Ltd v Universal Music Australia Pty Ltd [2006] FCA 1 (5 January 2006)
 http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/1.html

 application for leave to appeal
 authorisation of multiple infringements of copyright established
 prior sale of realty of one respondent to primary proceedings
 payment of substantial part of proceeds of sale to offshore company in purported repayment of loan
 absence of material establishing original making and purpose of loan
 mareva and ancillary orders made by primary judge  orders made requiring filing of further affidavits of disclosure and cross-examination of one respondent to primary proceedings on her disclosure affidavit
 no error in making further ancillary orders
 leave refused
 practice and procedure



 Background to the current application

1 The applicants Sharman Networks Ltd ('Sharman Networks'), Sharman License Holdings Ltd ('Sharman License') and Ms Nicola Anne Hemming ('Ms Hemming') are each the subject of asset preservation orders made by Wilcox J on 22 March 2005 ('the Mareva orders').
 When referring to the applicants generally, I will do so as 'the Sharman applicants'.
 Each of the Sharman applicants was one of ten respondents to infringement of copyright proceedings brought by the present respondents ('the Music companies') in respect of the operation of what was described by the parties as the 'Kazaa system' ('the primary proceedings').
 Wilcox J made orders ancillary to the Mareva orders on 22 March 2005 requiring each of the Sharman applicants to disclose on affidavit the description and value of all of their assets, wherever situated, and to specify whether those assets were held by each applicant either beneficially or in trust for any other person or entity.
 2 Wilcox J delivered judgment on the complex issues of liability arising in the primary proceedings on 5 September 2005 ( Universal Music Australia Pty Ltd v Sharman License Holdings Ltd (2005) 220 ALR 1).
 In the meantime, Ms Hemming had filed two disclosure affidavits pursuant to Wilcox J's orders of 22 March 2005 whilst Sharman License and Sharman Networks had unsuccessfully sought several stays on various grounds of that same order insofar as it applied to them (see Universal Music Australia Pty Ltd v Sharman License Holdings Ltd [2005] FCA 406 per Hely J, delivered 8 April 2005; Universal Music Australia Pty Ltd v Sharman License Holdings Ltd [2005] FCA 441 per Wilcox J, delivered 15 April 2005 and Sharman License Holdings Ltd v Universal Music Australia Pty Ltd [2005] FCA 505 per Moore J, delivered 28 April 2005).
 Disclosure affidavits were eventually sworn on behalf of Sharman License and Sharman Networks by Mr Gee on 19 April 2005, which were later superseded by further affidavits sworn also by Mr Gee on 16 June 2005.
 Sharman License and Sharman Networks had also unsuccessfully sought an enlargement of time in which to file an application for leave to appeal from Wilcox J's orders of 22 March 2005 (see Sharman License Holdings Ltd v Universal Music Australia Pty Ltd [2005] FCA 802 per Lindgren J, delivered on 17 June 2005).
 3 On 24 May 2005, the Music companies filed a further amended notice of motion seeking further orders ancillary to the Mareva orders, which application was heard over several days by Moore J and determined by his Honour on 17 November 2005 substantially in favour of the Music companies ( Universal Music Australia Pty Ltd v Sharman License Holdings Ltd [2005] FCA 1587).
 The Sharman applicants acknowledge that the orders made by Moore J pursuant to that determination were interlocutory in nature.
 What had led to the Music companies' application for those ancillary orders were deficiencies in the asset disclosure affidavits provided by the Sharman applicants pursuant to the ancillary orders of Wilcox J made on 22 March 2005.
 It is from Moore J's interlocutory judgment of 17 November 2005 that the Sharman applicants presently seek leave to appeal, pursuant to O 52 r 10(2) of the Federal Court Rules .
 4 The principal orders made by Moore J on 17 November 2005 were as follows:


 '1.
 The applicants have leave to cross examine [Ms Hemming] on the affidavits filed and served by her in response to Order 5 of the orders of Wilcox J made on 22 March 2005, on such matters as the Court may later direct.






 2.
 [Ms Hemming] file and serve, within such time and [sic] the Court may specify, an affidavit that discloses with particularity the description and value of all the assets of [Sharman Networks] (and its subsidiaries within the meaning of section 9 of the Corporations Act 2001 (Cth) that are wholly owned) wherever situated and specifying whether those assets are held by [Sharman Networks] (or such wholly owned subsidiaries) beneficially or in trust for any other person or entity and further specifying:



 a. in the case of any bank accounts which [Sharman Networks] (or such wholly owned subsidiaries) controls, the name of the bank in which the account is held, the name of the branch, the name of the account, the name of a person in whose name the account is held, the account number, and the balance of the account as at the date of service of the orders;

 b. the name and address of any person or entity who holds any assets on trust or as nominee for [Sharman Networks] (or such wholly owned subsidiary);

 c. details of any trust or arrangement pursuant to which such assets are held;

 d. details of any charge, mortgage or other security grouped in relation to any asset; and

 e. details of any contracts entered into for the sale, mortgage, charge or other disposition of the assets or any part thereof or interest therein.


 3.
 Order 1 made by Wilcox J on 22 March 2005 is varied by inserting before the words "other than" the following words:

 (and, as to [Sharman Networks], be restrained from causing or permitting any wholly owned subsidiary to dispose of, to remove from Australia or to deal with in any way any of that subsidiary's money, property or other assets in or outside Australia)".
 '



5 The immediate background to much of the debate presently raised by the Sharman applicants, and as a consequence the principal focus of their attack upon the orders of Moore J below, concerned the existence of alleged shortcomings in the asset disclosures, and in particular the implications of a payment of $1,116,405.63 made by Ms Hemming to a Vanuatu company, Trustees International Limited ('TIL'), following upon the sale of the Sydney residence of Ms Hemming and Dr Kilmer-Barber for $2,100,000 on 4 February 2005, being a payment made purportedly by way of repayment of a loan.
 The Music companies' case presented to Moore J below was that there was in fact no such antecedent loan, that the transfer of such funds by Ms Henning to TIL in Vanuatu constituted a sham loan repayment, and that such funds have therefore continued to be her own moneys on the footing presumably of a constructive trust, and should have been identified as such in her affidavit of disclosure of her assets made pursuant to the Mareva orders.
 Although Moore J declined to make a finding in relation to the issue as to ownership of that fund, his Honour formed the view that he would permit cross-examination of Ms Hemming on matters concerning the fund, by reason of doubts attending the same.
 His Honour reasoned in that regard at [37] of his reasons for judgment as follows:

 'In all, real doubts arise about, and uncertainty surrounds, the reason why this transaction took place when it did and whether the monies transferred to TIL were, in truth, in satisfaction of a loan or continues to constitute an asset of, and requires disclosure by [Ms Hemming].
 Greater clarity about this matter may arise from the cross-examination of [Ms Hemming].
 '

 Legal principles informing the grant of leave to appeal

6 Section 24(1A) of the Federal Court of Australia Act 1976 (Cth) stipulates that an appeal shall not be brought from a judgment of the Court constituted by a single judge, being a judgment that is interlocutory in nature, unless the Court or a Judge gives leave to appeal.
 Although s 24(1A) does not purport to qualify or limit the Court's discretion (see D&eacute;cor Corporation Pty Ltd v Dart Industries Inc (1991) 33 FCR 397 at 399 in the joint reasons for judgment of Sheppard, Burchett and Heerey JJ), the Courts have developed general principles which inform the exercise of the discretion to refuse or grant leave to appeal from an interlocutory judgment.
 The rationale for those principles is the public interest in the efficient administration of justice, and the maintenance of 'the integrity and vigour of the procedures of the court, including as they do, the immediate involvement of the judge at all stages in the progress of cases to trial' ( Bomanite Pty Ltd v Slatex Corp Australia Pty Ltd (1991) 104 ALR 165 at 173, per Gummow J).
 One consequence sought to be avoided is the expansion of expensive and delaying pre-trial litigation involved in appeals on issues of practice and procedure, and the concomitant reduction in the authority of the trial judge, should such appeals be frequently entertained ( Bomanite at 176, per French J).
 7 At least for those reasons, this Court has held on a number of occasions that typically a party seeking leave to appeal from an interlocutory judgment ought to establish, first, that in all the circumstances, the decision from which leave is sought to appeal is attended with sufficient doubt to warrant the same being reconsidered by the Full Court, and secondly, that substantial injustice would result if such leave was to be refused, supposing the decision to have been wrong: see D&eacute;cor at 398.
 That those two questions were the touchstone of exercise of discretion in matters of this kind was common ground between the parties.
 I observe that it is well accepted that those criteria are not to be applied rigidly or fixedly, and the Court must bear in mind all of the circumstances of the particular case: see in that regard Adam P Brown Male Fashions Proprietary Limited v Phillip Morris Incorporated [1981] HCA 39 ; (1981) 148 CLR 170 at 177, where Gibbs CJ, Aickin, Wilson and Brennan JJ said:

 'For ourselves, we believe it to be unnecessary and indeed unwise to lay down rigid and exhaustive criteria.
 The circumstances of different cases are infinitely various.
 We would merely repeat, with approval, the oft-cited statement of Sir Frederick Jordan in re the Will of F B Gilbert (dec) (1946) 46 SR (NSW) 318 at 323:



 "...I am of the opinion that...there is a material difference between an exercise of discretion on a point of practice or procedure and an exercise of discretion which determines substantive rights.
 In the former class of case, if a tight rein were not kept upon interference with the orders of Judges of first instance, the result would be disastrous to the proper administration of justice.
 The disposal of cases could be delayed interminably, and costs heaped up indefinitely, if a litigant with a long purse or a litigious disposition could, at will, in effect transfer all exercises of discretion in interlocutory applications from a Judge in chambers to a Court of Appeal.
 "



 ...It is safe to say that the question of injustice flowing from the order appealed from will generally be a relevant and necessary consideration.
 '


8 It was the Music companies' contention that the orders of Moore J, from which leave to appeal is now sought, determined matters of practice and procedure within the foregoing statements of principle, involving as they did the obligation of Ms Hemming to submit to cross-examination on affidavits made by her in early April of this year, and to file a separate affidavit disclosing the assets of Sharman Networks.
 Those obligations were said to be no different in principle to any other interlocutory procedural order of the court, whether made pre-trial or during a trial, requiring parties to swear affidavits, to answer questions in cross-examination and to provide documentation.
 On the question of what constitutes 'substantial injustice' for the purposes of determining an application for leave to appeal, counsel for the Music companies placed particular reliance upon the decision of the Full Federal Court delivered earlier in the primary proceedings, which denied leave to appeal from a decision by Wilcox J refusing to set aside Anton Piller orders that his Honour had earlier made: Brilliant Digital Entertainment Pty Ltd v Universal Music Australia Pty Ltd (2004) 63 IPR 373.
 I will refer further to that authority shortly.
 9 The Sharman applicants sought to emphasise the existence of practical burdens imposed by the orders made by Moore J on 17 November 2005, although in reality it was principally with respect to the order for cross-examination of Ms Hemming to which that assertion was directed.
 They maintained that the requirement to appear for cross-examination was not analogous to the 'routine steps' of swearing an affidavit during the normal course of a trial and entering the witness box to answer questions related to its contents.
 Rather, the requirement to be cross-examined on an asset disclosure affidavit was said to be 'at the extreme end of the Court's armoury', by virtue of the fact that the making of an order for cross-examination on an affidavit of this kind is predicated upon the Court having implicitly found the deponent of that affidavit to be in contempt of court.
 I was referred by the Sharman applicants to an earlier Full Federal Court decision in Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs v Wong [2002] FCAFC 327 in support of their submission that since the present circumstances give rise to an important question of principle, leave to appeal should be readily granted.
 The parties' respective submissions concerning material matters bearing upon the justification or otherwise for the grant of orders ancillary to the Mareva relief and my incidental observations

10 The affidavit filed in support of the application for leave to appeal by Mr Rohan Higgins, the solicitor for the Sharman applicants, contained the following broad submission under the heading '[i]njustice if leave is refused':

 'If leave to appeal is not granted then the orders of Moore J will operate and will have to be complied with.
 Any subsequent challenge to those orders would then be futile and academic.
 The orders are interlocutory in form but final in the result in relation to the issues raised.
 '


So much is correct as a general statement as to the consequences of his Honour's orders.
 However, the nature and context of the application for leave here involved in practical terms an appeal, or virtually so, as will hereafter emerge.



11 The Music companies contended that the Sharman applicants' submissions proceeded in reality 'on the erroneous basis that every interlocutory decision that requires a party to do an act will be automatically susceptible to leave to appeal and to being stayed'.
 The Music companies' position was that the orders requiring Ms Hemming to file an affidavit disclosing the assets of Sharman Networks, and to attend for cross-examination on the affidavit she had earlier sworn as to disclosure of her assets, were merely procedural in nature and therefore, incapable as such of determining any final rights of the parties.
 So much accorded with Moore J's understanding of the nature of those orders, as indicated in [30] of his Honour's reasons for judgment.
 12 The primary submission made by the Music companies as to why leave to appeal ought not to be granted related to the failure of the Sharman applicants to adduce evidence demonstrative of the claim that they would suffer 'substantial injustice', should leave be refused.
 The Music companies rejected any notion to the effect that the mere fact of Ms Hemming being compelled to swear an affidavit as to disclosure of Sharman Networks' assets, and to attend for cross-examination upon her own disclosure affidavits, without more, amounted to 'substantial injustice', in the sense that such expression has been used in numerous authorities concerned with the grant of leave to appeal.
 Reference was made to Gerlach v Clifton Bricks Pty Ltd [2002] HCA 22 ; (2002) 209 CLR 478, in which Gaudron, McHugh and Hayne JJ, in a different context, considered that the bare proposition that an order mandating 'trial by judge alone, as opposed to trial by judge and jury, can amount, without more, to a substantial wrong to a party or to a miscarriage of justice, [was] a startling proposition'.
 The reality of the dilemma in which the Court is placed by the present application is the need for consideration in some depth of the matters to which attention has been drawn by the Sharman applicants, before determining whether leave to appeal ought formally to be granted to appeal in the first place.
 The Sharman applicants relied upon a further passage from the majority's reasons for judgment in Gerlach at [13], as follows:

 'The principles governing the grant of leave to appeal against interlocutory orders are well established...If it is plain that wrong principle was applied by the judge considering the application, it may well be that leave should be granted...'


13 The Music companies, for their part, placed particular reliance upon the joint reasons for judgment of Black CJ and Stone J in Brilliant Digital for the approach that they contended ought to be adopted in my consideration of the present application for leave to appeal.
 In refusing leave to appeal from Wilcox J's decision to decline to set aside earlier Anton Piller orders that had been made in the course of the subject litigation, their Honours were said not to have considered at all the merits of the contemplated appeal there in issue.




